Campus E1 5, Saarbruecken, Germany 66111 vaastav@mpi-sws.org, https://vaastavanand.com/

Research Interests

I like building, testing, breaking, and fixing systems.

My primary research interests lie at the heart of cloud computing, focused on building more performant cloud systems and diagnosing performance issues in such systems. I am also interested in the performance reliability of Post-Moore heterogeneous hardware systems in the context of cloud systems.

Education

PhD, Computer Science

2020-current

Max Planck Institute for Software-Systems (MPI-SWS), Saarbruecken, Germany

MSc, Computer Science

2018-2020

University of British Colombia, Vancouver, Canada

Thesis: Dara the explorer : coverage based exploration for model checking of distributed systems in Go

BSc, Computer Science

2013-2018

University of British Colombia, Vancouver, Canada

Selected Research Projects

Iridescent 2022-current

Iridescent is a library that provides developers a systematic way for developers to support generalization while also taking advantage of specialization optimization opportunities arising from the workload and the deployment environment.

Blueprint (fka Millenial)

2020-current

A framework for developing flexible and modular microservice applications.

Provides a programming abstraction for writing microservice applications that makes it easy to later change aspects related to the system's scaffolding and topology.

Publications

Papers

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Deepak Garg, Antoine Kaufmann, Jonathan Mace. Blueprint: A Toolchain for Highly Reconfigurable Microservice Applications. In Symposium on Operating Systems Principles, **SOSP 2023**.

Lei Zhang, Zhiqiang Xie, <u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Ymir Vigfusson, Jonathan Mace. The Benefit of Hindsight: Tracing Edge Cases in Distributed Systems. In Networked Systems Design and Implementation, **NSDI 2023**.

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Zhiqiang Xie, Matheus Stolet, Roberta De Viti, Thomas Davidson, Reyhaneh Karimipour, Safya Alzayat, Jonathan Mace. The Odd One Out: Energy is not like Other Metrics. In **HotCarbon 2022**.

<u>Vaastav Anand*</u>, Puneet Mehrotra*, Daniel Margo*, Margo Seltzer. Smooth Kronecker: Solving the Combing Problem in Kronecker Graphs. In Joint Workshop on Graph Data Management Experiences and Systems and Network Data Analytics, **GRADES-NDA 2020**.

Pedro Las-Casas, Giorgi Papakerashvili, <u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Jonathan Mace. Sifter: Scalable Sampling for Distributed Traces, without Feature Engineering. In Symposium on Cloud Computing, **SoCC 2019**.

Pre-Prints

Jakob Görgen, <u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Hejing Li, Jialin Li, and Antoine Kaufmann. Columbo: Low Level End-to-End System Traces through Modular Full-System Simulation. In arXiv 2024, https://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.05251.

Puneet Mehrotra*, <u>Vaastav Anand*</u>, Daniel Margo, Milad Rezaei Hajidehi, and Margo Seltzer. SoK: The Faults in our Graph Benchmarks. In **arXiv 2024**, https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.00766.

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Matheus Stolet, Thomas Davidson, Ivan Beschastnikh, Tamara Munzner, and Jonathan Mace. Aggregate-driven trace visualizations for performance debugging. In arXiv 2020, https://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.13681.

Posters

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>. Online specialization of systems with Iridescent. At Student Research Competition at Symposium on Operating Systems Principles, **SRC @ SOSP 2024**.

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Antoine Kaufmann, Deepak Garg, Jonathan Mace. Millenial: Modular Microservice Macrobenchmarks. At Operating Systems Design and Implementation, **OSDI 2022**.

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>. Millenial: Modular Microservice Macrobenchmarks. At Student Research Competition at Symposium on Operating Systems Principles, **SRC @ SOSP 2021**.

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>. Millenial: Modular Microservice Macrobenchmarks. At Eurosys Doctoral Workshop, **EuroDW 2021**.

Pedro Las-Casas, Giorgi Papakerashvili, <u>Vaastav Anand</u>, Jonathan Mace. Sifter: Scalable Sampling for Distributed Traces, without Feature Engineering. At Symposium on Cloud Computing, **SoCC 2019**.

<u>Vaastav Anand</u>. Dara: Hybrid Model Checking of Distributed Systems. At Student Research Competition at The ACM Joint European Software Engineering Conference and Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering, **SRC @ ESEC/FSE 2018**.

Employment

Research Intern, Microsoft

2024

Azure Research - Systems

- Worked on "Automated Service Design with LLMs" project.
- Mentors: Rodrigo Fonseca, Alok Gautam Kumbhare
- Collaborators: Pedro Las-Casas, Celine Irvene, Jonathan Mace, Gagan Somashekar, Chetan Bansal

Research Intern, MPI-SWS

2019

• Instrumented DeathStarBench applications with XTrace tracing for large-scale experiments for Sifter.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

University of British Columbia, Under Ivan Beschastnikh

• Designed and developed Dara, a tool for model checking distributed systems.

Software Engineering Intern, NVIDIA

2017

MODS (Modular Diagnostics) Team

- Implemented memory repair sequences for faulty High Bandwith Memory (HBM).
- Designed, developed and implemented a CUDA based full memory stress test.

Software Engineering Intern, NVIDIA

2016

MODS (Modular Diagnostics) Team

• Implemented a synchronization option for CUDA based lineack tests to synchronize CUDA kernel launches within 30us across multiple GPUs.

Software Developer Intern, Thinkbox Software

2015-2016

Sequoia Team

• Designed, developed and implemented the 3D PDF export option in Sequoia.

Teaching

Teaching Assistant, Saarland University

2021

• 1 semester TA for Distributed Systems (Core Course)

2021

Graduate Teaching Assistant

2018-2020

University of British Columbia, Department of Computer Science

- 1 semester TA for Computer Hardware and Operating Systems (CPSC 313) 2020
- 1 semester TA for Graduate Operating Systems (CPSC 508) • 1 semester TA for Distributed Systems (CPSC 416)

2019 2018

2018

Academic Assistant Vancouver Summer Program

• Teaching Assistant for the Algorithms and the World Wide Web course.

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

2014-2018

University of British Columbia, Department of Computer Science

- 1 semester TA for Introduction to Software Engineering (CPSC 210)
- 2018 2017
- 1 semester TA for Advanced Operating Systems (CPSC 415)
- 1 semester TA for Intermediate Algorithm Design and Analysis (CPSC 320) 2017
- 1 semester TA for Computer Hardware and Operating Systems (CPSC 313) 2016
- 1 semester TA for Introduction to Computer Systems (CPSC 213) 2015
- 3 semesters TA for Models of Computation (CPSC 121) 2014-2015

Awards

1st Place, Graduate Catgeory, SOSP'24 SRC

2024

SoCC Student Scholarship

2019 2018

2nd Place, Undergraduate Category, FSE'18 SRC

2018

SIGSOFT CAPS Award **UBC** International Tuition Award

2018-2019

Work Learn International Undergraduate Research Award

2018

UBC Faculty of Science, International Student Award

2015, 2018

ACM ICPC PacNW Regional Contest Division 2 Champion

2017

UBC Trek Excellence Scholarship

2016-17, 2017-2018

UBC Dean's Honor List

2014, 2015, 2017

UBC Computer Science Student Service Award

2015

GIIS Global Citizen Scholarship

2011-2013

Service

Academic Service

- Program Committee Member
 - CS-Can Student Symposium 2019
- Organizer
 - Tutorial on using Blueprint to accelerate Microservice Research @ SOSP'24
 - Panel on Reproducibility and Replication @ HotOS'23
- Publicity Chair
 - The Journal of Systems Research 2022-2023.
- Systems Trivia Co-Organizer
 - HotOS 2023
 - SOSP 2021
 - HotOS 2021
- Organization Committee Member
 - The Cornell, Maryland, Max Planck Pre-doctoral Research School (CMMRS) 2022

Invited Talks

Blueprint: A Toolchain for Highly-Reconfigurable Microservices

Jun 2024

Event: Azure Monitor Day of Learning @ Microsoft Redmond

Host: Kalyana Sundaram

Blueprint: A Toolchain for Highly-Reconfigurable Microservices

Aug 2023

Event: Trustworthy Systems Seminar @ UNSW Sydney

Host: Peter Chubb

Blueprint: A Toolchain for Highly-Reconfigurable Microservices

Aug 2023

Event: Basser Seminar Series @ University of Sydney

Host: Zhanna Sarsenbayeva

Millenial: Modular Microservice Macrobenchmarks

Jun 2021

Event: Tracing Jamboree @ Emory University (virtual)

Organizers: Avani Wildani, Ymir Vigfusson

Skills

Programming Languages: C++, Go, Python, C, Bash, JavaScript, Java, CUDA

Tools: IntelliJ, GDB, Eclipse, Visual Studio, Git, Perforce, Vim, LATEX

Selected Non-Research Projects

Distributed Clocks

2018-2020

Inter-operable vector clock logging library

- Distributed clocks implements vector clocks in Go, Java, C++ and C
- https://github.com/DistributedClocks

Datasets

- Vaastav Anand. Fantasy Premier League Gameweek-By-Gameweek Dataset. https://github.com/vaastav/Fantasy-Premier-League
- Vaastav Anand and Jonathan Mace. X-Trace trace dataset for DeathStarBench. https://gitlab.mpi-sws.org/cld/trace-datasets/deathstarbench_traces

Interests Computing: Distributed Systems, Operating Systems, Software Engineering Extra Curricular: Soccer, Linguistics, Cricket.